<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Help id="0">
  <Intro id="1" title="Overview">
DeSERt V1.0 alpha

Question?
Contact me at: bildstein.johannes@gmail.com

DeSERt uses:
#RawTherapee:     http://rawtherapee.com/
#Exiftool:        http://www.sno.phy.queensu.ca/~phil/exiftool/
#SharpZipLib:     http://www.icsharpcode.net/opensource/sharpziplib/

© 2012 Johannes Bildstein</Intro>
  <Howto id="1" title="How to use DeSERt">
The workflow of DeSERt with Raw Therapee.
    <Step id="2" title="Before DeSERt">
Preparations before you start DeSERt:

Before you start DeSERt you have to edit one (or more for keyframes)
picture of your set in Raw Therapee.
When you are finished doing that simply save the PP3 file (Postprocessing profile)
by clicking on the save button on the right side below the histogram.</Step>
    <Step id="2" title="First Start">
First start of DeSERt:

When you first start DeSERt you have to choose the Path to your
desired editing Software (currently only Raw Therapee).
Simply do that by clicking on “Settings” in the Menu.
And while you´re there you can check the other settings too and set them as you wish.</Step>
    <Step id="2" title="Loading Images">
Loading the Images:

The First thing you have to do for a new project is, of course,
loading the images you want to process.
Click on “Add Images” and choose the directory with your set.
The program will load every image with known image extension in this directory.
It may take a while till all thumbs and camera information is loaded.</Step>    
    <Step id="2" title="Postprocessing Profile">
Choosing the Postprocessing Profile:

When the images are loaded you can choose the previously saved PP3 file and open it.
If your set of images needs changes in editing over time, simply make more PP3s which
you can add with a right click on the desired image in the table and choose "Keyframe->Add".
If you have added more than one Postprocessing Profile, DeSERt will interpolate all values
inbetween (you can still change the interpolation manually at the editing tab).</Step>
    <Step id="2" title="Filtersets">
Adding and Making Filtersets:

This feature is not completely finished yet but will be soon.
    </Step>
    <Step id="2" title="Darkframes">
Adding Darkframes:

With right clickon the table and "Darkframe->Open" you can select between three options:
1. Single Image: Adds a Darkframe to the selected image.
2. Till End: Adds the opened Darkframe to all following images, starting from the selected one
3. Till Nex Darkframe: Adds the opened Darkframe to all following images until the next opened Darkframe, starting from the selected one
For removing a Darkframe there are the same options.
    </Step>
    <Step id="2" title="Brightness Calculation">
Starting the Brightness Calculation:

If you have the right set of images loaded you can start the calculation of the brightness.
You can cancel this operation by clicking on the “Cancel” button.
After the calculation you have the possibility to adapt the brightness as you wish. There are
two ways to do that:
1. Directly change the brightness value in the table.
2. Use the slider in the editing tab. It changes the whole curve in percent.
To reset changes from the first option, use right click->Brightness->Reset (All) Brightness.
To reset changes from the first option, either use the "Reset Curve" Button to completely
reset the curve or simply type in "100" in the box over the slider to only set back the slider.</Step>
    <Step id="2" title="Curves">
Set various Curves:

Once you have calculated the brightness you can also start to edit the curve. If you have selected the
"Exposure_Compensation" curve you see two curves in the graph. The blue one is the calculated brightness
and the green one is how the output brightness will be, you can also edit this one.
If you have opened one or more PP3s there are many more curves to select from. If you have added more than
one PP3, you can encounter red points in the graph. Those points mark a keyframe and you can´t edit them.

The "End = Start" Button sets the last point to the value of the first point and the "Start = End" Button
does the same just vice versa.
The "Reset Curve" button sets the curve back to its initial form.</Step>
    <Step id="2" title="Brightness Preview">
Using the Brightness Preview:

Before you start to render your whole sequence you may want to check if the brightness correction is accurate.
The "Startindex" indicates the image where the check should start and the "Count" value sets how many images
should be rendered for the preview. When the brightness calculatin is finished, the startindex is automatically
set to the highest brighntess jump (where you usually can see an error best).
Click on the "Brightness Preview" button to start rendering the preview and wait till it is finished.
Now a window pops up and you can use the slider on the bottom to switch between the images and check if a
correction is necessary.
Note that you may get different (and probably better) results if you have opened a postprocessing profile.
This is due to the fact that the WB and the vignetting correction has a great effect on flicker.</Step>
    <Step id="2" title="Saving">
Saving the Images:

When you´re done with everything simply click on the “Save” Button and Raw Therapee will start the editing.
The finished files will be saved to your selected folder.
If you wish that the computer goes to sleep mode or completely shuts down, select the desired option beside the button.</Step>
    <Step id="2" title="After DeSERt">
When the images are edited:

Once all images are finished you can close DeSERt and continue further processing as you wish.</Step>
  </Howto>
  <Issues id ="1" title="Known Issues">
  Known Issues, Bugs and Problems:

  #the little thumbs probably won´t show up after loading images
  #interpolation of curve (custom) is not completely accurate (if 4 or more pp3s are used)
  #the graph curves doesn´t show up if you have opened a Postprocessing Profile but the brightness isn´t calculated yet
  #identifying the colorspace of an image doesn´t work without Exif (standard = sRGB)
  #using the Brightness Preview doesn´t work without exif (it´s used to get the image size)
  #the X/Y valueboxes can´t be set and show an high/low error at the infolabel (it gets set back when redrawing the graph somehow)
  #The bitdepth of the output is always 8bit. It´s not possible yet to set that via commandline (not implemented in Raw Therapee yet)
  ->Workaround: Keep the generated PP3 and start batch processing with RT manually (there you can set the output to 16 bit)</Issues>
  <Planned id ="1" title="Planned Features">
Features that I want to implement sooner or later:
    
#implementing Lightroom support (DeSELt -> Deflicker Software with Exiftool and Lightroom)
#option to correct WB jumps (from changing filters)
#option to add a filterset to an image -> better handling for correcting WB jumps, filter corrections... (this info is then written to the PP3/XMP)
#Drawing two slim red lines which shows the compensationability of RT/LR
#check for installed Rawtherapee/Lightroom and location automatically at the first start
#When an Error happens, try to save open Project and ask to open it after new startup
#make it possible to use ctrl+z/y</Planned>
</Help>